Guide to the Jesse Pyrant Andrews photographs and oral histories, 1973-2020 RL.00043
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Virginia, 1975-2017; 4.0 Linear Feet 61 photographic prints; 23 CD-ROMs; 13.11 Gigabytes 46 audio files 23 .mp3 files; 23 .wav files
  - Interior of curing barn, old Carter farm, Halifax County, Virginia, 2014 September (Box 10, Image RL00043_P_181)
    Here are the small fires Robert Wooding sets in the barn to cure his dark-fired tobacco. Part of the smoke necessarily escapes from the cracks and holes in the barn, sometimes giving the mistaken impression that the barn is afire. When the growing of dark-fired tobacco was more common, fire departments sometimes got false calls reporting a burning barn.
  - Robert Wooding plowing his garden beside the old Carter farm home, 2012 (Box 10, Image RL00043_P_182)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 125-27
    The Carter house was built in three sections, the first (middle) section around 1790. The front section was added about 1840, and the kitchen, a log-bodied room, was added in 1886. Legend has it that the huge rock chimneys flanking the original section were built by a woman, although her name is long forgotten. Robbie's grandmother, Elizabeth Carter, was the last permanent resident of the house. Robbie still uses the kitchen. The rest of the house is used as a guest house and family gathering place.
  - Kitchen, old Carter farmhouse, 2016 January (Box 10, Image RL00043_P_183)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 154-16
  - Hallway, old Carter farmhouse, 2016 January (Box 10, Image RL00043_P_184)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 154-4
  - Farm sale, Easley farm, Pittsylvania County, Virginia, 1976 October (Box 10, Image RL00043_P_185)
    Orig. print number: JA/FA 7-1.
    This was the first farm sale I photographed. This sale was of the Easley homeplace, where my ancestor Pyrant Easley, born in 1742, settled and built his home in 1772, after leaving Halifax County, Virginia, where he orginally settled around 1764. He was a son of John Easley, who settled in Cumberland County, Virginia, circa 1735. The Easleys were Huguenots who fled France in the late 1600s, after Louis XIV revoked, in 1685, the Treaty of Nantes, which had granted vast privileges to the Huguenots. More than 10,000 Huguenots left France for America at that time. Pyrant Easley the elder died in 1816, leaving the home and several hundred acres of land to his son, also named Pyrant, born 1805. The younger Pyrant's grandson, Robert Henry Easley, was my grandfather. Robert's brother, Jesse Pyrant Easley, for whom I am named, was living in the original homeplace on the farm when he died in 1975 at age 91, leaving no will. Consequently, the farm was sold at public auction. A cousin bought the property at the sale, and so it remains in the family still. No one now lives in the original house, but is is being well maintained by the fmaily. It is one of two early homes in Pittsylvania County that were built in an "H" configuration. The Pittsylvania Easleys have always farmed tobacco, and continue to do so even now.
  - Farm sale, Pearson farm, Climax, Virginia, 2004 (Box 10, Image RL00043_P_186)
    Orig. print number: JA/FA 21-5A.
    Originally settled by John Richmond Pearson. He married Alsee Boswell, born 1883. Alsee was the older sister of my maternal grandmother, Vivian Boswell, born 1903. Vivian married Robert Easley in 1920 (see notes regarding the Easley farm sale). The Pearsons had eleven children, most of whom stayed on the farm and raised tobacco. One son, Thomas was killed when he was struck by lightning while plowing with a mule. John and Alsee's children are all deceased, although some descendants still live on the farm. Tobacco is no longer grown on that land. The homeplace, scene of this photograph, burned to the ground in April, 2016.
  - Dr. Roger Browne, South Boston, Virginia, 2017 April; 4 items 1 print; 3 CDs (Box 11, Image RL.00043_P_187, Digital-materials RL.00043-SET-0001u, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0023.MP3, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0024.MP3, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0025.MP3)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 169-6A
    Dr. Browne served as an Army surgeon in the Central Highlands of Vietnam, 1968-1969. First assigned as Battalion Surgeon to the 146th of the 198th Light Infantry Brigade, he had charge of 36 medics and worked primarily from LZ Bayonet and LZ Professional, near Chu Lai. He was later promoted to Brigade Surgeon of the entire 198th. He was present when LZ Professional was overrun by North Vietnamese troops on two occasions.
    Accompanied by an oral history. Part of the Vietnams Project.
  - Garland Andrews Lowrey, Halifax County, Virginia, 2016 December 20; 3 items 1 print; 2 CDs (Box 10, Image RL.00043_P_188, Digital-materials RL.00043-SET-0001u, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0026.MP3, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0027.MP3)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 167-35
    Andy Lowrey spent 14 months as an infantryman, in the Central Highlands of Vietnam, from October 1968 until December 1969, primarily in and around Dragon Valley, near Chu Lai. Assigned to the 1/46th of the 198th Light Infantry Brigade, he, like Dr. Browne, was on LZ Professional when it was overrun by North Vietnamese troops.
  - Robert Aiken, South Boston, Virginia, 2017 February 9; 2 items 1 print; 1 CD (Box 10, Image RL.00043_P_189, Digital-materials RL.00043-SET-0001u, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0022.MP3)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 168-7
    Ninety-six year old Robert Aiken was part of a unique division of men who were trained by the Army specifically for the planned invasion of Japan in 1945. Told in training that they could expect 75% casualties on landing, they were nevertheless willing to go through with their mission. Mr. Aiken is an exceptionally cheerful man who has spent his life helping other people.
  - William Haskell Egan III, a longtime friend, at his home near Charlottesville, Virginia, 1975 (Box 10, Image RL.00043_P_190)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 169-5
  - Norma Reed Smith, 2003 (Box 10, Image RL.00043_P_191)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 99-6
    Born in Sparta, N.C., in 1917, Norma moved with her family to Danville, Virginia, at age 5. She began working at the Dan River Fabric Mill in 1932, at age fifteen. After seven years she was assigned to work in the spinning room, where she worked for the next forty years. She married Oscar Smith in 1946 and raised two sons, Jerry and Dennis. Norma died 7 November, 2005.
  - Jerry Donald Smith, 1987 (Box 10, Image RL.00043_P_192)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 61-17
    Eldest son of Norma and Oscar Smith. A writer, currently living in Danville, Virginia.
  - James Matthew Aaron on his 65th birthday, Callands, Virginia, 2012 December 7 (Box 10, Image RL.00043_P_193)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 133-24
    Born in 1947, Jim was the eldest son of Matthew Lafayette Aaron (see entry for earlier image). Because of a difficult birth, Jim was delivered with forceps, resulting in his having a minor deformity of his eyes. He also walked with a slight limp. Because the other children made fun of him, his father took him out of school after the first grade. He became his father's shadow and learned farming - how to grow a crop of tobacco, how to raise cattle, how to repair cars and machinery. Jim had an unfailing memory for details and loved Nascar and working with horses. After Mr. Aaron's death, Jim's health began to decline, and he died of congestive heart failure in 2015.
  - Claude Swanson Shelton, Gretna, Virginia, 1976 (Box 10, Image RL.00043_P_195)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 43-4
    Born in Pittsylvania County, Virginia, in 1892, "Swannie" Shelton was my grandmother's first boyfriend. He played the fiddle and banjo, and, along with my grandmother's four brothers, had a string band. They played at house parties, dances, corn huskings, barn raisings, and weddings...just about any occasion that called for music, playing what we now know as "old time." The band broke up when Giles Boswell, my grandmother's brother, who, according to Swannie, was "a first-rate fiddle player," was killed in France at the second battle of Verdun. In the 1970s, my grandmother and I often visited Swannie at his barber shop in Gretna, where we would play a few tunes and the two of them would talk about "the old days." Swannie died in 1982. The street in Gretna where he had lived for years was named "Music Street" in his honor.
  - Floyd Martin Fox, Sr., Weal, Virginia, 1980 (Box 10, Image RL.00043_P_196)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 61-4
    Floyd Fox was born in 1905. He farmed for a while as a young man, then went to work on a railroad construction crew. When he injured himself in a fall from a bridge, he returned to the farm and opened a store "on the road" in 1932. He sold farm supplies, seed, fertilizer, food, had a bar with slot machines, and sold gasoline. He used to boast that he had the oldest ABC license in Virginia. He extended credit to his farmer neighbors, and when the CCC established a camp nearby, his business became a popular place for the men in the camp to come and relax in the evening... [see inventory in box for more details]
- Burlington Mills, 2013-2016; .5 Linear Feet 7 photographic prints; 4 CD-ROMs; 1.61 Gigabytes 8 audio files 4 .wav files; 4 .mp3 files
  These seven black-and-white portraits by photographer Jesse Andrews and the oral histories that accompany them form part of the Burlington Mills Project, which documents the lives of former employees of a Halifax, Virginia textile mill, and how they and their community have been affected by the mill's closure in 2002. The gelatin silver prints measure 11x14 inches, and are arranged in chronological order and then by original identifiers as assigned by the photographer.
  The recorded oral history interviews accompanying the photographs have been migrated to a library server. They can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library reading room. As they require advance preparation, please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use these materials.
  Original media (oral history CDs) are closed to use. Digital listening copies are available. Please contact the Rubenstein Library for access.
  - Burlington Mill site, Halifax, Virginia, 2013, prior to demolition (Box 7, Image RL00043_P_156)
    Orig. print number: JA/BUR 1-6
  - Parking lot, Burlington Mills fabric plant, Halifax, Virginia, 2013 September (Box 7, Image RL00043_P_157)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 145-33
  - Cissy Tingen Martin and Geneva Andrews, Halifax, Virginia, 2014 January; 2 items 1 print; 1 CD (Box 7, Image RL00043_P_158, Digital-materials RL.00043-SET-0001u, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0015.MP3)
    Cissy Martin and Geneva Andrews both worked at the Burlington Mills plant in Halifax, Virginia. Ms. Martin now works as a hair stylist. Ms. Andrews drives a bus for the Halifax County school system.
    Two oral history interviews accompany this print, both on one CD.
    The oral history is available for research use. As it requires advance preparation for access, please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use this material.
  - Lott Rogers, Halifax, Virginia, 2014 February; 2 items 1 print; 1 CD (Box 7, Image RL00043_P_159, Digital-materials RL.00043-SET-0001u, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0003.MP3)
    Orig. print number: JA/BUR 1-8
    Lott Rogers, now a financial consultant in Halifax, Virginia, was the plant manager at the Halifax Burlington Mills fabric plant when that plant closed in 2002.
    This print is accompanied by an oral history interview on CD.
  - Frank Lee, Halifax, Virginia, 2015 September; 2 items 1 print; 1 CD (Box 8, Image RL00043_P_167, Digital-materials RL.00043-SET-0001u, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0011.MP3)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 162-23
    Frank Lee worked in as the Human Resources manager at the Burlington Mills fabric plant in Halifax from 1969 until 1977. This is part of the ongoing Burlington project.
    An oral history accompanies this print.
  - Mae Moorefield, South Boston, Virginia, 2016 January (Box 10, Image RL00043_P_175)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 164-15
    93 year old Mae Moorefield went to work at the Halifax Damask mill at age 15, where she trained as a weaver. When Burlington Mills opened their Halifax plant in 1948 she went to work there as an instructor for new weavers. She worked at Burlington for forty years. Part of the Burlington Project.
    Oral history accompanies this print.
  - Harold Young, Halifax County, Virginia, 2016 February and April; 2 items 1 print; 1 CD (Box 10, Image RL00043_P_176, Digital-materials RL.00043-SET-0001u, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0021.MP3)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 164-27A
    Harold Young worked at the Halifax Burlington Fabric Mill from 1958 until 1998. Harold is an accomplished musician and the son of Inez Young (her portrait is also in the collection). Part of the Burlington Project.
- Life at Large and Other Work, 1973-2020; 3.5 Linear Feet 54 prints; 4 CD-ROMs; 1.4 Gigabytes 4 audio files 2 .wav files; 2 .mp3 files
  The oral history interviews accompanying the photographs have been migrated to a library server. They can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library reading room. As they require advance preparation, please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use these materials.
  Original audiovisual media closed to use. Digital listening copies are available. Please contact the Rubenstein Library for access.
  Series houses 54 11x14 inch black-and-white (gelatin silver) photographs. Most document people, culture, and landscapes of central Piedmont North Carolina and Virginia. One portrait is of a Vietnam Veteran, Joe Wilcosky, and includes an oral history. The rest of the photographs were taken in New York State, California, and Massachusetts. Images feature street scenes in Boston, buildings, and natural subjects such as plants and ice on a pond.
  Other "Life At Large" images are also found in the Virginia series, marked in the legacy identifiers as "LAL." Photographs of some of the same people in this series can also be found in the Portraits series.
  - Street scene, Boston, Massachusetts, with sleeping man, 1973 June (Box 5, Image RL00043_P_111)
    Print originally unnumbered.
  - Street scene, Boston, Massachusetts, 1973 October (Box 5, Image RL00043_P_112)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 44-27
  - Broadway Hand, Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1974 April (Box 5, Image RL00043_P_113)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 44-4A
  - North End, Boston, Massachusetts, 1974 (Box 5, Image RL00043_P_114)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 40-9
    This woman operated a tiny bakery with the help of her son in the Italian section of Boston. They made marzipan, cannoli, and other pastries, as well as several kinds of bread, all wonderful.
  - Boston, Massachusetts, 1974 (Box 5, Image RL00043_P_144)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 121-5A
    Elderly woman standing in front of a store holding a tract titled "AWAKE."
  - Boston, Massachusetts, 1974 (Box 5, Image RL00043_P_145)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 4-34
    Children playing in the courtyard of an apartment building.
  - Boston, Massachusetts, 1974 (Box 13, Image RL00043_P_225)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 165-29
    A street scene in the North End.
  - Boston, Massachusetts, running man, 1974 (Box 14, Image RL00043_P_234)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 168-20
  - Boston, Massachusetts, running child, 1974 (Box 14, Image RL00043_P_235)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 168-12
  - Boston, Massachusetts, 1975 (Box 5, Image RL00043_P_146)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 44-5A. Clothesline with clothes hanging on it, with a garden beneath.
  - At the Lincoln Memorial, 1976 July 4 (Box 14, Image RL00043_P_236)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 6-9
  - Jimmy Carter on television, 1977 (Box 10, Image RL00043_P_198)
    In the parlor of my parents' home.
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 132-2
  - Charlottesville, Virginia, 2001 (Box 5, Image RL00043_P_148)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 21-14
    Man walking across a parking lot, seen through partially opened curtains.
  - Abandoned grist mill, Riceville, Virginia, 2001 (Box 5, Image RL00043_P_149)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 35-7
    Wooden building with the window closed in with a sign reading "FIN."
  - Times Square, New York City, 2003 July (Box 6, Image RL00043_P_121)
  - Street preacher, New York City, 2003 July (Box 6, Image RL00043_P_122)
  - Kudzu house, 2003 (Box 6, Image RL00043_P_123)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 58-4
  - Plant shadow, 2003 (Box 6, Image RL00043_P_124)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 59-16
  - Adam's needle (yucca plant), 2003 (Box 6, Image RL00043_P_125)
    Orig. print number: JA/NAT 4x5-16
  - New York City, 2003 July (Box 6, Image RL00043_P_126)
    Unnumbered.
  - 45th St. at Broadway, New York, 2004 December (Box 6, Image RL00043_P_127)
  - Plant shadow, 2004 (Box 6, Image RL00043_P_128)
  - Storefront, 7th Avenue, New York City, 2004 December (Box 6, Image RL00043_P_129)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 78-31
  - Pond ice, 2007 (Box 6, Image RL00043_P_130)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 106-53
  - New homes for sale, 2007 (Box 6, Image RL00043_P_131)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 77-15
  - At the Statue of Liberty, 2009 (Box 14, Image RL00043_P_237)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 89-10
  - At Covesville, Virginia, 2009 (Box 14, Image RL00043_P_238)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 74-29
  - Danville, Virginia, 2010 (Box 6, Image RL00043_P_147)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 97-16
    Storefront with the painted image of a bearded black man. Sign reading "Sanctuary."
  - Sign attached to the old Halifax County jail building, Halifax, Virginia, 2017 January (Box 10, Image RL00043_P_197)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 157-16
  - Statue of Robert E. Lee covered with a tarp, Lee Park, Charlottesville, Virginia, 2017 September (Box 12, Image RL00043_P_199)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 159-28
    Whatever Lee believed, he has now become a symbol...signifying to some people an ancestral nightmare and to others an ancestral hero. Likewise the catchword "heritage" carries vastly different meanings depending on what one's ancestors were doing or having done to them 157 years ago. After he died, however, his image as a popular Southern hero overshadowed his own desire in life to put the past behind him. The tarp covering Lee's statue was removed in March of 2018 by order of Judge Richard Moore. The issue is still being debated by the Charolttesville city council.
  - Statue of Robert E. Lee covered with a tarp with sleeping man in foreground, Lee Park, Charlottesville, Virginia, 2017 September (Box 12, Image RL00043_P_200)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 159-18
  - Statue of Confederate soldier, erected by the United Daughters of the Confederacy in the early 20th century, Halifax County Courthouse, Halifax, Virginia, 2017 September (Box 12, Image RL00043_P_202)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 158-27
    Hundreds of statues similar to this one were put up across the South by the UDC in the years just before WWI and in the 1920s. The Halifax County Courthouse is slated for extensive renovation which will drastically alter the historic façade of this building. Built in 1838 by Dabney Cosby, the building is on the National Reister of Historic Places. This statue will probably be removed as a part of the renovation.
  - Mountain View Plantation home, Tightsqueeze, Virginia, 2018 January (Box 14, Image RL00043_P_239)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 165-24
  - At Mountain View Plantation, Tightsqueeze, Virginia, 2018 March (Box 12, Image RL00043_P_201)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 161-37
    Shows a corner of a room interior with a bust of Robert E. Lee, and on the wall, the first and second Confederate flags, and three sabers.
  - SPACE BLASTER. Found in the parking lot at BO's One Stop, Halifax County, Virginia, 2018 March (Box 12, Image RL00043_P_205)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 160-28
  - Mike Smith operating the sawmill at the Old Carter Farm, Halifax County, Virginia, 2006 June (Box 12, Image RL00043_P_211)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 2 3-30
    Set up in the early 1960s by Robert Wooding, Sr., this sawmill has produced thousands of board feet of lumber from trees sustainably harvested on the Carter Farm. It is still being used.
  - At Mountain View Plantation, Tightsqueeze, Virginia, 2018 September (Box 13, Image RL00043_P_220)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 163-13
    Built in 1790, Mountain View was the home of a lifelong friend, Steven Law, who died unexpectedly September 1, 2018. Mountain View was owned by generations of Steven's family. I spent many days and nights there in the 66 years I knew Steven. To be at Mountain View was to transcend time and place. He owned this 1960 Corvette, and drove it for many years, often exceeding 140 mph. He parked it in the yard at Mountain View in 2002, believing that if he continued his thrill-seeking it would eventually kill him. It is currently returning to the earth, as is Steven.
  - At Mountain View Plantation, 2018 April (Box 13, Image RL00043_P_221)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 161-28
    A fourth-story window, looking south toward the family cemetery. Steven attempted to preserve Mountain View as it had always been. Plumbing and electricity were added by his parents in the 1930s. Otherwise it remains basically unchanged.
  - Mountain View, ruins of the old overseers' office, 2018 June (Box 14, Image RL00043_P_240)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 169-33
  - The kitchen building at Mountain View, 2018 September (Box 13, Image RL00043_P_222)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 163-4
    Originally this building housed the kitchen, separated from the main house in case of fire. Steven's father James Law, an architect, used it for his office.
  - West exterior elevation, Mountain View, 2018 September (Box 13, Image RL00043_P_223)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 163-6
  - At Mountain View, 2018 November (Box 13, Image RL00043_P_224)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 164-23
    View of the parlor window, looking west.
  - At Mountain View, from Laura's window facing north, 2019 February (Box 14, Image RL00043_P_241)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 167-31
  - Trumpster dumpsters, Halifax County, Virginia, 2019 June (Box 14, Image RL00043_P_242)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 169-25
  - Billboard, Halifax, Virginia, 2019 (Box 14, Image RL00043_P_243)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 165-35
  - Frank Joseph Wilcosky, Jr., Halifax County, Virginia, 2018 (Box 16, Image RL00043_P_245, Digital-materials RL.00043-SET-0001u, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0078.MP3, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0079.MP3)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 153-33
    Joe grew up in Fort Lauderdale, Florida. He joined the U.S. Navy at age 17, served on a destroyer (USS Cory) and an aircraft carrier before volunteering for riverboat duty in Vietnam in 1967. He was assigned to the Mobile Riverine force at Dong Tam, an American base south of Saigon in the Mekong Delta, and served there 1968-1969. The Riverines served as support troops for the 9th Inf. Division, also based at Dong Tam, ferrying troops upriver to firefights and lending support, often going ashore to participate in the fighting when the 9th Inf. Troops got into a tight spot. Joe was a jack of all trades, serving in whatever capacity was needed, everything from fighting fires during the daily mortar and rocket attacks at Dong Tam to accompanying troops upriver. Discharged in 1969, he returned to Fort Lauderdale and worked as a postal carrier until his retirement after 29 years. Joe now lives part time in Fort Lauderdale and part time here in Halifax Co. He is a close friend.
    Part of the collection is restricted: original media are closed to use.
  - Front entrance, Mountain View plantation homeplace, Tightsqueeze, Virginia, 2019 (Box 16, Image RL00043_P_250)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 171-4